<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Academic Website Julius Koschnick</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_645fa481986063ef.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology and the age of sail</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/scikit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/scikit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/small&gt; &lt;em&gt;Picture &amp;mdash; The view from the rigging from the replica of the Götheborg&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reflections on technology, skills, and the age of sail after my voyage on the Götheborg as part of the crew, take a look at this Twitter thread:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/juliuskoschnick/status/1562395926970376192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;See the summary on X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am further glad that there is an active interest in maritime history within our field of economic history. Please find a small collection of publications on maritime economic history:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;North, D. (1958). Ocean freight rates and economic development 1730-1913. The Journal of Economic History, 18(4), 537-555.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harley, C. K. (1971). The shift from sailing ships to steamships, 1850–1890: a study in technological change and its diffusion. In Essays on a mature economy: Britain after 1840 (pp. 215-237). Routledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pascali, L. (2017). The wind of change: Maritime technology, trade, and economic development. American Economic Review, 107(9), 2821-2854.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kelly, M., &amp;amp; Ó Gráda, C. (2019). Speed under sail during the early industrial revolution (c. 1750–1830). The Economic History Review, 72(2), 459-480.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arteaga, F., Desierto, D., &amp;amp; Koyama, M. (2024). Shipwrecked by rents. Journal of Development Economics, 168, 103240.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Miotto, M., &amp;amp; Pascali, L. (2025). Solving the longitude puzzle: A story of clocks, ships and cities. Journal of International Economics, 155, 104067.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, in my humble opinion, these two classics cannot miss in such a list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rodger, N. A. M. (1999). The safeguard of the sea: A naval history of Britain, 660–1649 (Vol. 1). W. W. Norton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rodger, N. A. M. (2005). The command of the ocean: A naval history of Britain, 1649–1815 (Vol. 2). W. W. Norton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list is unauthorative and just intended as a simple help for anyone interested in maritime history. Should I have missed a (your) publication, please send me an email and I will be most happy to add it to the list.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The English universities in the 17th century</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/pandas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/pandas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Picture: Magdalen College in 1566 from Foster’s Alumni Oxonienses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventeenth-century universities stood at the intersection of medieval and modern regimes of knowledge production. On one hand, curricula remained largely rooted in scholastic and Aristotelian traditions—particularly in England. On the other hand, universities continued to serve as key sites of intellectual exchange. A central mechanism of this exchange was the vertical transmission of ideas between teachers and students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://juliuskoschnick.com/publication/preprint---copy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Teacher-directed change: The case of the English Scientific Revolution&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, I argue that despite their traditionalism, the universities of Oxford and Cambridge played a critical role in passing on the ideas of the Scientific Revolution to a new generation of scholars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a short summary of the paper here (or just head to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ehes.org/wp/EHES_274.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; itself):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I’m happy to announce that my JMP🚨🚨Teacher-directed change: The case of the English Scientific Revolution” is now out as a working paper. Finalising the draft has been a lot of work. So, very happy to share this! For lots of history, new micro-data&amp;amp;natural experiments, read on &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hTX2CKhj5C&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/hTX2CKhj5C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julius Koschnick (@JuliusKoschnick) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JuliusKoschnick/status/1904153755253084438?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 24, 2025&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or listen to this NotebookLM podcast here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio controls preload=&#34;none&#34; style=&#34;width:100%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/audio/podcast.wav&#34; type=&#34;audio/wav&#34;&gt;
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
